Finding Aid for Housing Division (University of Michigan) Records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Microfilm
  - Housing Monthly Reports to the Vice President for Student Affairs
    - December-January 1985 (Reel 2)
    - December-September 1984 (Reel 2)
    - December-January 1989 (Reel 2)
    - December-January 1990 (Reel 2)
  - Residence Hall Libraries Annual Reports
    - 1984/85 (Reel 2)
    - 1982/83 (Reel 2)
    - 1980/81 (Reel 2)
    - 1979/80 (Reel 2)
    - 1977/78 (Reel 2)
    - 1976/77 (Reel 2)
    - 1973/74 (Reel 2)
  - Housing Procedure Manual 1976 (Reel 2)
- Program Director
  The Program Director Files (2.0 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically and appear to be created by Ed Salowitz and Peter Ostafin. File headings have been named to be as consistent as possible with the previous accessions.
  Items of particular interest are the "Historical Background Files" and the "Reports." The "Historical Background Files" contain considerable information on the evolution of residential housing, male and female. The "Dormitory Histories" file contains fact sheets on each of the dormitories. The fact sheet contains information on the individual that the dormitory was named in honor of, cost and description of the building, date of completion, information on the houses within the dorm, and any special programs within the unit. Reports and surveys have been combined under the heading "Reports." The reports, which span the years 1925 through 1990, include such topics as living conditions for students, graduate student housing, and studying in residence halls. Many of the files within this series fill the gaps that are found in previous accessions.
  - Topical Files 1925-1997
    - Academic Counseling Program in Residence Halls 1974 (Box 38)
    - Additional Student Housing Task Force 1971-1986 (Box 38)
    - Annual Report to the President, 1970/71-1987 (Box 38)
    - Bicycle Discussion Group 1979-1982 (Box 38)
    - Bike Control Program 1965-1969 (Box 38)
    - Board of Governors of Residence Halls 1943 (report of the subcommittee) (Box 38)
    - Co-educational Housing Study Committee 1970 (Box 38)
    - Credit Union Co-op Housing 1970-1977 (Box 38)
    - Discipline 1979 (Box 38)
    - Evaluation Committee 1979-1980 (Box 38)
    - Fall Planning Committee 1979 (Box 38)
    - Facility Renewal & Capital Improvements Program 1991 (Box 38)
    - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) re: housing policies 1979-1990 (Box 38)
    - Greek Task Force Report 1986 (Box 38)
    - Historical Background Materials
      - Dormitory Histories undated (Box 38)
      - Family Housing 1996 (brief history of) (Box 38)
      - Max Kade German House 1980 (Box 38)
    - Historical Background Materials (cont.)
      - Men 1939-1951 (historical) (Box 38)
      - Michigan Union 1952 (social history) (Box 38)
      - University Housing 1980 (Box 38)
      - Student-Faculty Council circa 1966 (Box 38)
      - Women 1956-1961 (re: housing of women students) (Box 38)
    - Housing Assistance 1989 (Box 38)
    - Housing Facilities Department
      - Building Condition Summary 1991 (Box 38)
      - Customer Satisfaction Survey 1991 (Box 38)
      - Resident Satisfaction Survey 1991 (Box 38)
    - Housing Office 1970-1983 (general information) (Box 38)
    - Housing Statistics
      - First Semester Residence Credit Enrollment 1949-1994 (Box 38)
      - Miscellaneous 1930-1991 (Box 38)
    - Housing Strategy (minutes) 1985-1986 (Box 38)
    - Inter Cooperative Council
      - Advisory Board 1930-1963 (Box 38)
      - Development Committee 1961-1963 (Box 38)
      - Max Kade German House (Box 38)
        (SEE Historical Background Materials)
    - Living-Learning Committee, Report of 1973 (Box 38)
    - Michigan House Plan 1941 (Box 38)
    - Michigan Union (Box 38)
    - Monthly Report to the Vice President for Student Affairs
      - July 1987-June 1988 (Box 38)
      - August 1988-July 1989 (Box 39)
      - August 1989-July 1990 (Box 39)
      - August 1990-March 1991 (Box 39)
    - North Campus Community Center 1967-1977 (Box 39)
    - Occupancy Report
      - Family Housing 1989-1996 (Box 39)
      - International Students Report 1993 (Box 39)
      - Minority 1995 (Box 39)
      - Residence Halls 1991-1996 (Box 39)
    - Rates
      - Comparison to CPI (consumer price index) 1978 (Box 39)
      - Off campus 1980-1989 (Box 39)
    - Reports and Surveys
      - A Tentative Plan for the Promotion of Satisfactory Living Conditions and Social Contacts Among Students at UM, 1925 (Robert C. Angell) (Box 39)
      - After the Quads, Where? A Study of Student Housing Problems, and a Proposal for an Expanding University Housing Program, 1958 (Box 39)
    - Reports and Surveys (cont.)
      - Blue Ribbon Committee for Fair Rental Practices Report ca 1976 (Box 39)
      - Commuter Survey 1985/86 (Box 39)
      - Facility Renewal and Capital Improvements: A Review and Assessment for University Housing 1988 (Box 39)
      - Final Report of the Student Housing Study Committee of the Student Affairs Committee 1955 (Box 39)
      - Food Service Survey 1981 (Box 39)
      - General Housing Services Survey 1972-1973 (Box 39)
    - Reports and Surveys (cont.)
      - Housing at the University of Michigan: a Report of a Survey of American Students, 1965 (Box 39)
      - The Housing of Graduate Students at the UM, 1955 (Box 39)
      - The Housing of Students, 1979 (Box 39)
      - Junior Faculty Housing Survey, undated (Box 39)
      - Operation Inquiry, 1953-1957 (re: men's residence halls) (Box 39)
      - The Quality of Life for Minority Students in the University of Michigan Residence Hall, 1990 s (Box 39)
      - Report on the Results of the Community Focus Survey, 1987 (Box 39)
      - Residence Halls Survey, 1983-1984 (Box 39)
      - Student Housing at the UM: 1969, 1969 (Pelz report) (Box 39)
      - Student Housing Plans, 1982 (Box 39)
      - Student Opinion Survey of the East Quadrangle, 1960 (Box 39)
      - Students and Realtors in Ann Arbor Housing, 1965 (Box 39)
      - Study Locations and Grades, 1985 (Box 39)
      - Studying in the Residence Halls, 1985 (Box 39)
      - Survey of Ann Arbor Housing with Special Reference to Student Accommodation, 1945 (Box 39)
      - Survey of Landlords, Student Housing, 1970 (Box 39)
      - Voluntary Non-Returns 1960 (Box 39)
    - Residence Hall Based Academic Counseling Program 1974 (Box 39)
    - Residence Halls
      (See Also Historical Background Materials)
      - General 1940-1989 (Box 39)
      - Policies 1997 (Box 39)
      - Statistics 1949-1995 (miscellaneous) (Box 39)
    - Second Presidential Commission on Housing 1987-1989 (Box 39)
    - Senior Management Team 1993-1996, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Single Student Housing Rate Study Committee 1974-1975 (Box 39)
    - Special Study Committee for the Office of Student Affairs 1962 (Box 39)
    - Task Force on Faculty, Staff and Student Housing Issues 1989-1991 (Box 39)
    - Vice President for Student Affairs circa 1985 (includes history and purpose) (Box 39)
- Student Papers
  The Student Papers series (.3 linear feet) is arranged in chronological order and spans the years 1953-1992. The papers were written by university students for classes in Education, Political Science, History, and Economics. All of the papers relate to some aspect of housing at the University of Michigan. The series is RESTRICTED under the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA).
  - 1953 "Residence Halls for Men at the University of Michigan" (Richard McCaughey) (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2028 ]
  - 1964 "Low Cost Rental Housing Need in Ann Arbor" (Thomas H. Moore) (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2039 ]
  - 1965 "An Analysis of Supply and Demand in Apartment Housing: Central Campus Area, 1964" (Robert Bodkin) (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2040 ]
  - "City-University Relations" (Donald A. Morris) 1966 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, July 1 2041 ]
  - "City-University Relations" (Neill H. Hollenshead) 1966 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2041 ]
  - "The University and the City" (Alan Bloom) circa 1970 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2045 ]
  - "The Effects of Dormitory Architecture on the Living Patterns and Social Interaction of University Students" (Roland M. Binker) 1975 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2050 ]
  - "The Dissolution of the Office of Dean of Women the University of Michigan" (Mary Ann Wellman) 1980 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2055 ]
  - "Women's Housing and the Residence Hall Movement" (Sara H. Garmel) 1983 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2058 ]
  - "Student Housing Options in Ann Arbor" (Robert S. Hoy) circa 1985 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2060 ]
  - "MBA Housing Feasibility Study" (Skaff, Kieras, Leighton, Huck, and Campbell) 1987 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2062 ]
  - "Living at the University of Michigan" (Aldas Kriauciunas and Laurel Wright) 1988 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2063 ]
  - "A Solution to the Housing Dilemma" (Anne Baxter) 1988 (Box 40)
  - "The Identification of the Sources of Rental Cost Differences in Three Major University Cities in America" (Joseph M. Baremore) 1989 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2064 ]
  - "The History of Mary Butler Markley Residence Hall" (Preeti N. Malani) 1989 (Box 40)
  - "The Office of the Dean of Women at the University of Michigan" (Grace H. Kim) 1992 (Box 40)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2067 ]